<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Mostafa Higazy</title>
        <link>https://www.higazy.dev</link>
        <description>A blog about web development and programming</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Dec 2022 21:38:20 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <image>
            <title>Mostafa Higazy</title>
            <url>https://www.higazy.dev/favicon.ico</url>
            <link>https://www.higazy.dev</link>
        </image>
        <copyright>All rights reserved 2022</copyright>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Next.js and Tailwind CSS: A Powerful Combination for Building Scalable Applications]]></title>
            <link>https://www.higazy.dev/articles/nextjs-and-tailwindcss</link>
            <guid>https://www.higazy.dev/articles/nextjs-and-tailwindcss</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Next.js is a popular JavaScript framework for building server-rendered and statically-exported applications. It is built on top of React, which allows developers to create and manage complex user interfaces with ease.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Next.js is a popular JavaScript framework for building server-rendered and statically-exported applications. It is built on top of React, which allows developers to create and manage complex user interfaces with ease.</p>
<img alt="" srcSet="/_next/image?url=%2F_next%2Fstatic%2Fmedia%2Fblog.2f8e8106.webp&amp;w=1080&amp;q=75 1x, /_next/image?url=%2F_next%2Fstatic%2Fmedia%2Fblog.2f8e8106.webp&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75 2x" src="/_next/image?url=%2F_next%2Fstatic%2Fmedia%2Fblog.2f8e8106.webp&amp;w=2048&amp;q=75" width="1000" height="420" decoding="async" data-nimg="future" loading="lazy" style="color:transparent"/>
<p>One of the benefits of using Next.js is its automatic code splitting, which allows the application to load faster by only loading the necessary code for each page. This means that users don&#x27;t have to download the entire application at once, improving the overall performance and user experience.</p>
<p>Another advantage of Next.js is its built-in support for server-side rendering. This means that pages are rendered on the server and served to the user, instead of being rendered on the client-side using JavaScript. This can improve the initial load time of the page, as the content is already available to the user when the page is loaded.</p>
<p>In addition to its core features, Next.js also has a rich ecosystem of plugins and integrations that can help developers to build powerful and scalable applications. One such integration is with the popular CSS framework, Tailwind CSS.</p>
<p>Tailwind CSS is a utility-first CSS framework that allows developers to quickly build custom user interfaces without the need for complex CSS rules. It provides a set of low-level utility classes that can be composed together to create custom designs, without the need for custom stylesheets.</p>
<p>The combination of Next.js and Tailwind CSS allows developers to create fast and performant applications with customizable user interfaces. By using the automatic code-splitting and server-side rendering capabilities of Next.js, and the utility-first approach of Tailwind CSS, developers can focus on building great user experiences without being bogged down by complex front-end code.</p>
<p>In conclusion, Next.js and Tailwind CSS are a powerful combination for building fast and scalable applications with customizable user interfaces. By leveraging the benefits of both frameworks, developers can create high-quality applications that provide a great user experience.</p>
<p><strong>Resources to check out:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/nextjs/install-tailwind-css-in-next-js-37a56bd64fa7">Install Tailwind CSS in Next.js?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://dev.to/thenayak/rebuilding-medium-with-tailwindcss-nextjs-hh3">Rebuilding Medium With TailwindCSS &amp; Nextjs</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nextjs.org/">Next.js</a></li>
<li><a href="https://tailwindcss.com/">Tailwind CSS</a></li>
<li><a href="https://reactjs.org/">React</a></li>
<li><a href="https://reactjs.org/docs/hooks-intro.html">React Hooks</a></li>
<li><a href="https://reactrouter.com/">React Router</a></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Just getting started? Use the following code below in your terminal to create your first website:</strong></p>
<p><strong>Execute <a href="https://github.com/vercel/next.js/tree/canary/packages/create-next-app">create-next-app</a> with <a href="https://docs.npmjs.com/cli/v9/commands/npm-init">npm</a> or <a href="https://classic.yarnpkg.com/en/docs/cli/create/">Yarn</a> to bootstrap the example:</strong></p>
<pre class="language-powershell"><code class="language-powershell">npx create-next-app <span class="token operator">--</span>example with-tailwindcss with-tailwindcss-app
<span class="token comment"># or</span>
yarn create next-app <span class="token operator">--</span>example with-tailwindcss with-tailwindcss-app
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Deploy it to the cloud with Vercel:</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://nextjs.org/docs/deployment">Vercel Documentation</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Learn more about Next.js:</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://nextjs.org/docs/getting-started">Getting Started with Next.js</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>mostafa@higazy.dev (Mostafa Higazy)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Five key insights on the future of software engineering]]></title>
            <link>https://www.higazy.dev/articles/five-key-insights</link>
            <guid>https://www.higazy.dev/articles/five-key-insights</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[As the technology field continues to evolve rapidly, software engineers must stay on top of the latest trends and developments to remain competitive. In this article, I will explore five key insights that will shape the future of software engineering.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As the technology field continues to evolve rapidly, software engineers must stay on top of the latest trends and developments to remain competitive. In this article, I will explore five key insights that will shape the future of software engineering.</p>
<h2>AI &amp; machine learning</h2>
<p>The use of artificial intelligence and machine learning is becoming
increasingly prevalent in software development.
These technologies allow for the automation of many tasks,
such as code testing and debugging, which can save time and
improve the quality of software. However, one should be careful while using
them as they often produce logic errors, neglect best practices, and
misunderstand the question leading to misleading code.</p>
<p><strong>Resources to check out:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7Pq-S557XQU">Humans Need Not Apply</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.gravity-ai.com/">gravity AI</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=i6qL3NqFjs4">BUILD and SELL your own A.I Model! $500 - $10,000/month (super simple!)</a></li>
</ol>
<h2>Low-code &amp; No-code tools</h2>
<p>The concept of &quot;low-code&quot;/&quot;no-code&quot; development is rising in popularity
, as it allows for the creation of complex and straightforward software applications without
the need for extensive programming knowledge. This trend will make
software development more accessible to a broader range of individuals,
including those with little to no coding experience.</p>
<p><strong>Resources to check out:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://webflow.com/">Webflow</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wordpress.com/">Wordpress</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.wix.com/">Wix</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.shopify.com/">Shopify</a></li>
</ol>
<h2>Cyber Security</h2>
<p>The importance of security in the software will continue to grow even more.
As more and more personal and sensitive data is stored and transmitted
digitally, software must be designed and built with security
in mind. This will require software engineers to understand security best practices and technologies strongly. Due to recent events, I have observed
a considerable rise in security exploitation, and the importance of cybersecurity was highlighted.</p>
<p><strong>Resources to check out:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.netguru.com/blog/web-development-security">15 Critical Security Tips for Web Development in 2022</a></li>
<li><a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Learn/Server-side/First_steps/Website_security">Website security</a></li>
</ol>
<h2>Open Source Software</h2>
<p>The use of open-source software will continue to expand.
Not only does open-source software often have a strong community of contributors
and users, but it can also save organizations money and provide access to a
wide range of high-quality software components. Recent examples include ChatGPT by OpenAI
while it&#x27;s not open-source anymore it started as open-source. It is a testament to the power of open-source.</p>
<p><strong>Resources to check out:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@kristen.carter/25-best-open-source-web-development-tools-8358e51ef33b">25 Best Open Source Web Development Tools</a></li>
<li><a href="https://opensource.com/tags/web-development">opensource.com</a></li>
<li><a href="https://betterprogramming.pub/5-open-source-projects-which-can-redefine-web-development-in-2022-567e7e2a6d12">5 Open Source Projects Which Can Redefine Web Development in 2022</a></li>
</ol>
<h2>Collaboration</h2>
<p>The field of software engineering will become even more collaborative
and interconnected. As the lines between different technology disciplines
continue to blur, software engineers will need to work closely with
other professionals, such as data scientists and UX designers, to create
integrated solutions.</p>
<p>Overall, the future of software engineering is bright,
with exciting new technologies and opportunities on the horizon, despite the recent
downturn and hiring freezes. By staying up to date with the latest trends and
developments, software engineers can position themselves for success in this
rapidly-changing field.</p>
<p><strong>Just getting started? Use the following code below in your terminal to create your first website:</strong></p>
<p><strong>Execute <a href="https://github.com/vercel/next.js/tree/canary/packages/create-next-app">create-next-app</a> with <a href="https://docs.npmjs.com/cli/v9/commands/npm-init">npm</a> or <a href="https://classic.yarnpkg.com/en/docs/cli/create/">Yarn</a> to bootstrap the example:</strong></p>
<pre class="language-powershell"><code class="language-powershell">npx create-next-app <span class="token operator">--</span>example with-tailwindcss with-tailwindcss-app
<span class="token comment"># or</span>
yarn create next-app <span class="token operator">--</span>example with-tailwindcss with-tailwindcss-app
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Deploy it to the cloud with Vercel:</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://nextjs.org/docs/deployment">Vercel Documentation</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Learn more about Next.js:</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://nextjs.org/docs/getting-started">Getting Started with Next.js</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>mostafa@higazy.dev (Mostafa Higazy)</author>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Software Engineering and Technology: Latest Insights and Tips]]></title>
            <link>https://www.higazy.dev/articles/latest-insights-and-tips</link>
            <guid>https://www.higazy.dev/articles/latest-insights-and-tips</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Sep 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Software engineering and technology are constantly evolving, and it can take time to keep up with the latest trends and developments. This article will look at some of the most important insights and tips that every software engineer and technology enthusiast should know.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Software engineering and technology are constantly evolving, and it can take time to keep up with the latest trends and developments. This article will look at some of the most important insights and tips that every software engineer and technology enthusiast should know.</p>
<p>First, let&#x27;s talk about the importance of staying up-to-date with the latest
technologies. As a software engineer, you must constantly learn and adapt to new technologies and frameworks to stay competitive in the
job market. This means regularly attending conferences, workshops, and other
events to learn from experts and network with your peers.</p>
<p>Another important tip is to focus on building a solid foundation in computer
science and programming principles. While it&#x27;s essential to be familiar with the
latest technologies, having a solid understanding
of the fundamental concepts that underlie all software development is even more critical. This will not
only make you a better engineer, but it will also make it easier for you to
adapt to new technologies as they emerge. There are a lot of great resources out there for
learning the fundamentals of computer science.</p>
<p><strong>Resources to check out:</strong></p>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@NeetCode">NeetCode</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nand2tetris.org/">Nand2Tetris</a></li>
<li><a href="https://pll.harvard.edu/course/cs50-introduction-computer-science?delta=0">CS50 Harvard</a></li>
</ol>
<p>One of the biggest challenges facing software engineers today is the growing
complexity of systems and applications. As software becomes more
integrated and interconnected, it becomes increasingly difficult to
manage and maintain. That&#x27;s why it&#x27;s crucial to prioritize software
design and architecture and to focus on building systems that are
scalable, maintainable, and easy to understand.</p>
<p>Finally, it&#x27;s important to remember the human
element of software engineering and technology. As engineers, we are often so
focused on the technical aspects of our work that we forget about the people
using our systems and applications. That&#x27;s why it&#x27;s essential to
keep the user experience in mind and design intuitive and accessible systems.</p>
<p>In conclusion, staying current in software engineering and technology
requires a commitment to continuous learning and improvement. This means
staying up-to-date with the latest technologies, building a solid foundation
in computer science and programming principles, and prioritizing software design
and architecture. It also means considering the human element and
designing systems that are intuitive and easy to use. By following these insights
and tips, you can stay competitive and thrive in software
engineering and technology.</p>
<p><strong>Just getting started? Use the following code below in your terminal to create your first website:</strong></p>
<p><strong>Execute <a href="https://github.com/vercel/next.js/tree/canary/packages/create-next-app">create-next-app</a> with <a href="https://docs.npmjs.com/cli/v9/commands/npm-init">npm</a> or <a href="https://classic.yarnpkg.com/en/docs/cli/create/">Yarn</a> to bootstrap the example:</strong></p>
<pre class="language-powershell"><code class="language-powershell">npx create-next-app <span class="token operator">--</span>example with-tailwindcss with-tailwindcss-app
<span class="token comment"># or</span>
yarn create next-app <span class="token operator">--</span>example with-tailwindcss with-tailwindcss-app
</code></pre>
<p><strong>Deploy it to the cloud with Vercel:</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://nextjs.org/docs/deployment">Vercel Documentation</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Learn more about Next.js:</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://nextjs.org/docs/getting-started">Getting Started with Next.js</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <author>mostafa@higazy.dev (Mostafa Higazy)</author>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>